Welcome to this 2026 release wave two of
Business Central launch edition. This
video is about the updated Word addin
for document reporting.
We have an action-packed agenda uh going
all the way from the new version of the
data picker all the way down to theme
and header footer samples.
the data picker uh got a lot of love in
with UX improvements but I think uh you
will discover that there's a new major
thing happening which is called the
company information data set
so we are renovating a lot of the
business central reports and looking at
the report objects we noticed that there
is a lot of repetition in the data set
specifically around things that are
related to company information like
logo, your address and so on. So we
decided we wanted to ship that always.
So in the future when you need to create
a report uh with a word layout, you
don't need to encode any of the data uh
in company information that's available
for you right away. So here in the word
addin in the new data picker you can see
the third option is called company
information just like report information
and uh company information has all the
fields like company name addresses you
can fold out the addresses um so
anything you need there is available for
your layouts.
This is in particularly uh particular
useful when you create header footer
layouts which is typically where you
would put things either from the report
metadata in the report definition or
from the company uh information.
We also um worked on the table builder
which was in preview in the wave one and
it now supports editing and we also
added a lot of UX enhancements
um for the table builder.
So here in uh the word addin, I have an
existing table added to the document.
And if I go to the table builder icon
and choose that, voila. You can see that
I'm actually able to edit with the
wizard even in the table definition and
I can just do whatever I want and um and
go back to the document. So, a huge
timesaver. In the past that the table
builder would would just allow you to
put a table in, but now you can go back
if you needed to add a column or do
other things. During our work on
renovating um new layouts for reports,
we invented
um a design language of different kind
of building blocks that we can see are
going to be used again and again and
again on body layouts or word layouts.
And um so we have different types of
ways to format addresses, uh group
fields, how to format amounts, signature
lines if you need a signature, uh and
and notes. So here are some examples of
that directly in the word addin. We have
uh this group of design controls where
the first address control gives you
three different options for formatting
addresses. And the first option here
gives you the sender and receiver and a
shipping address in three columns, but
you can also have receiver only or um or
other choices. So So check that out and
and see if that um fits the with the way
that you want to to present um the body
uh structure in the body layout. We're
going to use these going forward for all
the new body layouts in Business
Central. Here
is the field group uh group. So we can
add a column grid um single or double
stacked uh ways to have these key value
pairs of a label and a data item. So in
the first example here I can choose say
I want to have four fields and that's
formatted here with a caption and a
value and so on. So if you want three it
will be three. If have two, it will be
formatted as two. But these are design
components that allow you to design uh
with the same layout across all your
body layouts. Uh amounts here are not
necessarily calculating things but but
visualizing calculations. Um in the
first option here, I chose a calculation
and that will give me some captions with
values. Um and you would see that in our
reports um all over the place.
signatures. This is something that we
have been using in the quality
management module. So there are two
types of a signature uh line. The first
here is uh with two like tune name and
uh caption. So this could be like
approver one approver two. That really
depends on the captions you put in here.
And finally, if you go to the notes um
icon, it open ups a dialogue how many
bullet point of notes you want in your
in your document and then it adds that
design component and now you just need
to add data to it. All right. So that
these are examples of design blocks that
we are adding not necessarily datab
bound for now just pure text but uh in a
way that that uh that you can have the
same uh the same structural layout of
your body layouts. The next is a logical
control. So the hide if is allows you to
hide or show content based on a boolean
value. later on you will actually be
able to set boolean expression based on
the data in the data set that uh
determines whether you want to hide or
show something. So for that here the
hide if false if I choose that I'll get
a menu that where I choose which boolean
value I want to use and this is also
where we'll have that little formula uh
language later and based on that
whatever is inside that content control
will then be hidden or shown based on
the value of this boolean.
The final two parts in the word addin
are for not for constructing body
layouts but for themes or for header
footer. So it's for the theme order
authors would probably be people working
in the communication department or back
office. Um, and here, uh, we added some
sample documents that allow you to kind
of see the changes of a theme on a on a
on a VE document like report. Let me
show an example of that. So here under
sample layouts for themes, we have added
an invoice, a pick list or an a report
showing outstanding uh numbers or
orders. If I just choose the first one
here, it shows kind of an invoice like
document. This is not an invoice layout
at at all, but this is using the styles
um that you are supposed to if you
change styles, text, uh fonts, colors.
Hopefully, uh when you do that, then
these this document will change
accordingly. So, this is an aid for you
as a theme designer uh to put a a
document that looks like a real uh
invoice, then do your theming and you
can see it works. And once you're happy,
you just save this as a dox maybe scrap
the content uh and upload it to business
central and now you have a theme. This
is the pick lists just a a different
version and outstanding orders and would
be an internal report if you want to
have themes for internal or external
looking reports.
I mentioned that you can upload these.
This happens in business central under
manage themes and header footer layouts.
So here you can add your either your
theme or your header footer layout. Um
and now they then they are available to
be used in Business Central.
The same story is for header footer
authors. If you need to want to create
new header footer layouts to be shared,
uh we ship I think eight 10 different
header footer layouts. If you want to
create your own, you can also get some
help from the word addin. Specifically,
if you create a new header footer layout
from Business Central, you get all the
company information
data set into that document. You take it
to Word and then you can use the header
or footer
um menus here to add some of our default
um header footer uh versions and then
you can modify them. Once you are happy
with it, you can then uh save this and
upload it back to Business Central as
your own header footer layout.
I mentioned uh probably a couple of
times the new data set called company
information. Um these are available in
every single layout. Um the company
information is just uh whatever is in
the company information card on Business
Central. Uh so you have access to the
name to the address your fax number if
that's a thing for you and uh similarly
this is this is not new this has been
there forever the report information
these are the metadata for the report so
the report name and so on you can put
that um into the document as well and
that's it just one more thing
if you want to learn more about how to
use the new word addin uh go to our
developer documentation landing page
aka.ms/bcde
developer. Scroll down to the section
about reporting and learn everything
there is to know about the new version
of the word edit.
That's it. Um have a great launch
edition. Hope you learn a lot from the
other videos. Everything related to
reporting uh there are links down here.
Uh there are two more in this uh video
series. Um, so I hope you want to watch
them as well. Yeah, that's it for now.
Thank you. Have a great day. Bye.